<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reward of the wicked preached in a sermon at Linfield in Sussex, and publi[she]d at the request of some welld[is]sed [sic] Christians / by Humphrey Everenden.</title>
            <author>Everinden, Humphrey.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10601.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4669</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23714764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23714764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26831</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26831)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1832:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reward of the wicked preached in a sermon at Linfield in Sussex, and publi[she]d at the request of some welld[is]sed [sic] Christians / by Humphrey Everenden.</title>
                  <author>Everinden, Humphrey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones for Robert Bird, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁷.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, stained and tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Punishment --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26831:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26831:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
            <p>THE REWARD of the Wicked.</p>
            <p>Preached in a Sermon at <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> in <hi>Suſsex,</hi> and publiſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> at the requeſt of ſome well di<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>By HVMPHREY EVERENDEN.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ECCLE. 11.19.</bibl>
               <p>Reioyce, O yong man, in thy youth, and let thine heart cheare thee in the dayes of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> youth and walke in the ſight of thine eyes, but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all theſe things, God will bring thee to iudgement.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES for ROBERT BIRD, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Bible in Cheape-ſide. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26831:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He meanes of edification in the holy Scripture (gentle Reader) may all be referred to three heads. Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for all. Conſolations for the oppreſſed. Threats, for thoſe that erre and are obſtinate. Theſe make a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord, whereby God laboured to draw mankind to this end. Heere haſt thou one ſtrane twiſted, viz. the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or death of the damned. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods mercies cannot alure thee to loue him, heere haſt thou his iudgement to ſcourge thee, that thou maiſt feare him, that begining thy wiſdome in feare, thou maiſt ſo learne to loue him, that his iudgements being bitter to thy taſt, may cauſe thee to ſeeke to try how good he is in his mercies. God giue his bleſſing to his owne ordinance, for thy good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt. <hi>Humphry Euerend<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26831:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
            <head>THE REWARD of the Wicked.</head>
            <head type="sub">A SERMON PREACHED at <hi>Linfield</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATH. 25.46.</bibl>
                  <p>And theſe ſhall goe into euerlaſting paine.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He recompence of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the reward of the wicked deſcribed, in this verſe are both decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be euerlaſting, the one embraceing, the other deſpiſing an eternall Maieſtie; theſe that ſhall goe into euerlaſting paine, are the mercileſſe, the cruell and hard hearted and with them all that goe not into life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26831:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
all thoſe that <hi>ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt deſcribing the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the damned,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th. 13.<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the parable of the Tares, ſheweth that by his Angels they ſhall be bound vp into bundles to be burned, teaching that they that partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate in ſinne, ſhall be partakers in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and further, that their iudgement ſhall be irreuocable, their miſery remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe their eſtate helpleſſe, for whom God bindeth, who can be able to looſe.</p>
            <p>Curious deuiſion of the words I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely omit, obſeruing the generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction which ariſeth out of the words, without wreſting of them, or digreſſing from the true meaning of them.</p>
            <p>The vngodly ſhall aſſuredly receiue the puniſhment of eternall damnation at the day of iudgement.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/>Doct.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine it further confirmed by ſundry places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>In the 13. of <hi>Mathew</hi> is taught that the Angels ſhall gather together the <hi>tares</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.42.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked <hi>and bind them into bundles to burne them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 20 of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> is ſhewed that <hi>death and hell</hi> (that is, the heires of <hi>death and hell) were caſt into the lake
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26831:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
of fire: which is the ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 21 of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that <hi>the fearefull, and vnbeleeuing, and the abominable, and murtherers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and all lyers ſhall haue their part in the lake which burneth with fier and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) ſhall be vpon the ſoule of euery one that doth euill, of the Iew firſt, and alſo of the Grecian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſolonians,</hi> that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt ſhall ſhew himſelfe from heauen, with his mighty Angels, In fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fier, rendring vengeance to them that doe not know God, and which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe the Iuſtice of God doth exact and inferre, that as euery man doth ſow,<note place="margin">1 Reſ.</note> ſo he ſhall reape, and therefore he that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the fleſh, of the fleſh ſhall reape cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, as one the other ſide, he that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the ſpirit, doth of the ſpirit reape e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</p>
            <p>How doth it ſtand with Gods Iuſtice to puniſh a temporall offence with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall puniſhment.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/>Queſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:26831:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/>Anſw.The wicked are iuſtly puniſhed for theſe cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe their ſinnes are the offence of an eternall maieſtie</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe they neglect an eternall good, propounded and ſet before them, which by obedience they may obtaine, and ſo chooſe eternall meſery through walking in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Becauſe if they did liue eternall, they would alſo ſin eternally.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Becauſe the damned doth ſinne etern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally their tranſgreſſion is coeternall with their puniſhment, as therefore they ſhall euer remaine in torment, ſo ſhall they for euer remaine in vnbeliefe, impenitencie, blaſphemy; ſo that their punniſhment is not larger then their ſinne deſeruing it.</p>
            <p>For the opening of this doctrine. 2 things are to bée conſidered.
<list>
                  <item>1 Wherein the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth.</item>
                  <item>2 How farre their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment extendeth.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, The damnation of the wicked ſtandeth in a twofold puniſhment called <hi>paena damni, et paena ſenſa,</hi> the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of loſſe, and the puniſhment of ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The puniſhment of loſſe is a ſeperation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26831:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
from the preſence of God, and from all ioyes and pleaſures attending the ſame. This is that which the Apoſtle teacheth, that they ſhall bée puniſhed with euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perdition, <hi>from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power:</hi> And how great a miſtery this is may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in that they that are ſeperated from Gods preſence are ſeperated from all ioy and pleaſure, betwéene which and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſorow and miſery there is no meane, <hi>for in Gods preſence</hi> (and not elſe where) <hi>is fullneſſe of ioy,</hi> and at his right hand (and no where elſe to be found) <hi>are pleaſures for euermore:</hi> and for this cauſe our Sauiour Chriſt accounteth it the greateſt happineſſe of the <hi>pure in heart</hi> that <hi>they ſhall ſee God,</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it not, the leaſt iudgment that ſhould befall him héere on earth, that he ſhould bee hid from <hi>the face of God.</hi> It <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were ſo greiuous to <hi>Cain</hi> to be ſeperated from the place of Gods worſhip héere on earth, which is but a tipe of the ſeperation in the life to come, oh how greiuous then muſt it néedes bée to the damned in the life to come, to be indéed excluded from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and happineſſe of the glorified.</p>
            <p>The puniſhment of ſcenſe is the infli<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26831:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
of torments and miſeries, both one ſoule and body, for this ſhall be the miſery of the damned, that they ſhall not reſt without ioy and ſorrow, but as they ſhall be depriued of all happineſſe, ſo ſhall they be oppreſſed with all vnhappineſſe, as they ſhall bée debarred of all delight and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo they ſhal be filled withall vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able torments. By many things are their torments expreſſed in the holy Scriptures moſt terrible and moſt painfull our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>their worme neuer dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and their fier neuer goeth out,</hi> and againe, <hi>caſt that vnprofitable ſeruant into vtter darkneſſe, there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, Math:</hi> 25.30. with many the like paraphraſes and denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions expreſſing the like. Now if nothing can be more terrible then vtter darkneſſe, being that plague of Egypt which next to the death of the firſt borne moſt of all mooued <hi>Pharoahs</hi> hard hart, if nothing more painfull inwardly then the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the heart, with the teeth of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, if nothing outwardly, then the heate and burning of fier, yea, if nothing more intollerable then the continuance of theſe torments without ceaſing or intermiſſion, then ſuredly by theſe deſcriptions the Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26831:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
would haue vs know, that the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the damned is moſt intollerable, and ſo great as the fury of Gods wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne can kindle, and the rage of Satan can inflict.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſons that the damned doe ſuffer, not onely the puniſhment of loſſe, but of ſenſe, that is, that they doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looſe the benefit of comfort, but are alſo tormented, are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the puniſhment of loſſe.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reaſ.</hi>
               </note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neglect and deſpiſe the true good grace and glory offered vnto them, yea, and God himſelfe, the fountaine of all good, and therefore it is equall and iuſt that their puniſhment extend to this, that they be ſeperated from God and his glory, from all good and happineſſe. For God will forſake them that forſake him,</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the puniſhment of ſenſe. Becauſe they haue choſen to follow that which is euill and forbidden vnto them,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Reaſ.</hi>
               </note> therefore it is iuſt, that the reward of their owne hands be giuen vnto them, yea, it is equall, <hi>that his owne iniquities take the wicked himſelfe, and that hee be holden with the cords of his owne ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the ſecond conſideration, how <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the puniſhment of the wicked doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26831:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
it is euident that it extendeth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to euery one, with out reſpect or differences of perſons or properties, to old, young, rich, poore, weake and mighty, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ignoble, wiſe and fooliſh, <hi>Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and anguiſh ſhall be vpon the ſoule of euery one that doeth euill, Rom.</hi> 2 9. And <hi>Tophet is prepared of old: it is euen prepared for the King; hee hath made it deepe and large. Eſay</hi> 30.33.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to euery part of the damned <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> both to ſoule and body, yea to euery part of either of them, ſo that not ſo much as <hi>Diues</hi> tongue can be frée from the heate of this torment. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.24.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to the vttermoſt extreamitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for it ſhall be the extreameſt torment that may bée, the breath of Gods fury kind<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling it, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30 33. and being without a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny pittying or commiſeration: <hi>For there ſhall be iudgement mercileſſe to him that ſheweth no mercy. Iames.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlie, to be without ceaſing or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion, ſo that it ſhall be reſtleſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as the refreſhing of a drop of water (which were a ſmall thing in ſuch a fier) to coole any part of the tormented, &amp; therefore our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith in th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place before named, <hi>that there worm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26831:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
dieth, and their fier neuer goeth out:</hi> the worme biteth ſo long as he liueth, and the fier tormenteth ſo long as he burneth. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifthlie, to eternitie, for it ſhall be euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> without end, and therefore it is not onely called fier to expreſſe the greatneſſe of it, but euerlaſting fier to expreſſe the continuancie of it, <hi>Math:</hi> 25.41. Which cauſeth me to remember what one ſayeth in his meditations, if the damned were to continue in their torments but a thouſand <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>houſand yeares, yet had they ſome hope, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f but ſo many yeares as there are ſtarres <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the skie, ſands on the ſea, graſſe on the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>round, and duſt on the face of the earth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the greateſt drought, yet there ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n end, nay if but ſo many thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and yeares as are ſtarres in the skie, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands on the ſea, graſſe on the ground and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt on the face of the earth, yet ſhould <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here be one day an end of their torments, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut their miſery is farre otherwiſe, for ſo many thouſand yeares being ended, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of thouſands are againe to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egin, which alſo euer ſhall begin, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſhall haue end.</p>
            <p>Now if it bée demaunded by the way <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hither there ſhall bée in hell materiall fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to the torment of the damned;<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/>Queſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26831:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->I anſwer, it is no point of faith, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neceſſary to ſaluation to know,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/>Anſw. yet fréely to deliuer my opinion, without <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pargement to the opinion of the con<gap reason="illegible" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>y minded, I ſée no reaſon to the contrary. For inſomuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body ſinneth with the ſoule, it is iuſt that it be puniſhed with the ſoule, now inſomuch as the Scripture haue expreſſed this torment of fier, I thinke it curioſitie to expound that by a figure, and to be faine to ſearch out an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other figuratiue ſpeech to finde a matter to torment the body, fier being apt to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and being the greateſt of all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, neither is it naturall that may be ſaid, that then there muſt by that reaſon be a materiall worme to gnaw, as well as fier to burne, for fier can torment the body, but a worme cannot torment the ſoule, and therefore that which cannot lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally be vnderſtood to be done, muſt be figuratiuly expounded, which expoſition that may be done, ſo vnderſtood, néede not but litterally to be expounded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note>This doctrine may be a powerfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to all wandring ſinners, that goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray after, the corruptions of their owne hearts, in the deſert paths of diſobedience, to returne vnto their God by true repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26831:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
leaſt they dye the death for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bedience, if the poore ſhéepe in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> did but know, that if they continue <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ng from their fould, they ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uredly bée deuoured of the Wolfe, they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould ſurely (although wanting reaſon) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the very conduct of ſenſe make haſt to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he cuſtody of their Sheep-heard, this then <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing moſt certaine, that all that goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tray from the wayes of God, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inue wandring, either till their day of their <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſitation be paſt, or till death take away <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e time and place of repentance, ſhall bée <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euoured of hell and deſtruction, oh how <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould this moue vs, ſpéedily to returne to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he fould of Chriſt, to waſh away our ſins <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith the teares of repentance, to redéeme <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e time, and to be warned, that they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome not into this damnation.</p>
            <p>Hence may all obſtinate and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent ſinners, to their terrour, ſée the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed end of all their wicked courſes by the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ternall damnation both of body and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ule.<note place="margin">4 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> What then ſhall become of all Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ters, Adulterers, Drunkerds, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, breakers of Gods Saboths, couetous <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth-wormes, Vſurers, Oppreſſors, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch like, that liue and dye in their ſinnes. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urely they ſhall be bound vp in bundles
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26831:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
to be burned, they ſhall goe into euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing paine, malefactors one earth hau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome hope after ſentance to eſcape <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> temporall puniſhment for men are dra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne by many meanes to reuoke their ſenten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and to grant their gracious pardons, but in this iudgement the damned haue to goe with God, who is feared by no mans dreatneſſe, altered by no reward, with whom is no chaunging or ſhadow of turning, and therefore his ſentence is vnreuocable neither after this life is there any time, place, or libertie of repentance: but as the trée falls ſo it lies, either to life or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
